When you’re building Appian applications,
you’ll come across situations
where you need to display the same
interface component or layout—for
example, a card designed a certain
way—for a dynamic list of items.
This is where you’ll use the
looping function a!forEach[].
For each item in a list, it evaluates
an expression and gives the result.
It’s especially helpful when you
don’t know how many items are in that
list, or the number changes often.
So, you could use it to dynamically
display repeated interface components,
create user filters from record data, or
calculate values across a list of records.
There are a lot of ways to use
this function, so get creative!
Now, let’s see how it works.
In an expression rule,
I’ll add a!forEach[].
It has two parameters:
items and expression.
First, items is the array that
you want to take action on.
I’ll set items as 1, 2, and 3.
Second, expression is the
expression that you want to apply
to each of the items in the list.
So, if I simply type 1 and click
TEST, the function returns 1 for
each of the three items in my list.
But when you’re using a!forEach[], you’ll
most likely need to reference the values
of the list items in your expression.
So you can, for example, display
record data in an interface component.
You’ll do this with function variables.
Function variables are available within
certain functions and have the domain fv!.
Use them as inputs to your expression.
There are a few different function
variables in a!forEach, like
fv!itemCount and fv!isFirst, that you
can use to reference the list items.
But let’s focus on fv!item,
which is the most common one.
Fv!item lets you reference
the current item in the list.
So, in the expression parameter,
if I replace 1 with fv!item, now
the function returns 1, 2, and
3—which are the items in the list.
You can also use fv!item to transform
your data in the way you need.
So, if I update the expression to fv!item
+ 1, I get 2, 3, and 4 as the result.
Next, let’s see how you can
use a!forEach[] to dynamically
display interface components.
In this scenario, Acme Automobile, a
commercial vehicle fleet, wants to display
a feed of the comments about a vehicle.
a!forEach[] is a perfect
way to achieve this.
It’s often used in interfaces to
display repeated components when
you don’t have a set amount of data.
In this case, each vehicle
can have a different number of
comments on it, and that number
varies as new comments are added.
To get started, I first built a child
interface for a single comment that
I’ll call into my parent interface.
I want to repeat this interface
for each comment on a vehicle.
It includes the user who added
the comment, a picture of their
avatar, the date and time of the
comment, and the comment itself.
In the parent interface, I already
added my local variable, local!comments.
Using the rule input vehicle
ID, a query gets all of the
comments on a particular vehicle.
I also set up the section layout,
so in the contents parameter, I
can go ahead and add a!forEach[].
For items, I’ll use my local
variable, local!comments.
This way, the items in my list are
the comments on a particular vehicle.
For expression, I’ll call the
comment interface I built.
This interface has the rule
input comment, which is used
to get the comment record data.
Because I want to use the data
for each comment, I’ll use fv!item
as the value for the rule input.
Now, this interface repeats the
comment interface for the two
different comments on this vehicle.
If I change the test value to a
different vehicle ID, you can see
that the interface now shows the five
different comments on that vehicle.
Great!
Another benefit of using a!forEach[]
is when you need to make a change
that applies to all components.
So, if I decide to change the style
of the name field, I can update it
once in the child interface, and
the change is immediately applied
to all of the comments in the feed.
It would take a lot longer if I
had separate text fields for each
name and had to manually update
all of the style parameters.
So, even if you do have a set amount of
interface components you’re repeating, you
can use a!forEach[] to save time building
by only configuring it once, like in
this key performance indicator pattern.
a!forEach[] is a versatile function.
When you’re building your apps,
think about how you can use it to
build more reusable, comprehensible,
and powerful rules and interfaces.
To learn more about Appian functions,
visit us at Academy Online.
And, you can get a free Appian
Community Edition environment
to try it out yourself.
Thanks for watching!